[Music]
hello and welcome to the first live
lecture of the course
so before we jump into things there's
just a couple logistics to
uh handle here the first one is that we
have a new website so if you check the
link in the description
there's a new official course website uh
and again this is something that anybody
in the world is
free to attend the lectures for if you
want to second we're going to be doing
the discussion
during this lecture through discord so
if you want to answer questions or ask
questions or interact with the other
professors
while i give this lecture the discord's
the place to do it
um questions will be fed to me and we
can pull them up on screen here
so for example it looks like last time
there were some people asking about some
of the functions i was using in the
notebook
uh which i failed to mention were custom
defined within that notebook
so if you just try and like open raw
julia to call destinate
it doesn't mean anything but it was just
this small little custom thing
and in general we'll share the notebooks
that we're using so if you want to
follow along you can see all those
pre-definitions
um and with that you know we only have
30 minutes for this lecture
convolutions are super interesting and
let you do a bunch of powerful things
so i say let us just jump right into
things
so as a first example i'm just going to
take this 8-bit mario
that we see this very low resolution
image and i want to blur it
and if you're thinking about blurring an
image maybe the first thing that you
could think to do
would be to look at each pixel and kind
of average it with all of its neighbors
and do this sort of moving average so
the way i'm doing it here we've got this
little grid
uh three by three grid of values that's
marching across the image
and slowly creating a new image on the
right and to be concrete what's going
on here is each of those values is 1 9
and we're sort of thinking of lining
them up with some pixels multiplying
each of those values by the
corresponding pixel
and then adding them together so in this
case if they're all 1 9 then we multiply
them and we add them together
we're just taking an average of the nine
pixels so in this
specific window it looks like there's
four black pixels
four gray pixels and then one that's
kind of the mario skin tone color
so you would expect the average to be
like a darker gray with the tiniest
you know hint of mario skin color and if
we go and look at the new
image that's being generated and what's
painted into that pixel
it's that it's a dark gray with the
tiniest hint of some kind of skin color
and as we keep marching along we get
this blurrier image of mario we might
zoom in on another example
um here you know this grid it's mostly
covering the skin color with just a
little bit of black
here and there so we would expect it to
be a dyed down version of that
which is what we see um and he's this
gives kind of a nice effect right
we zoom out and we see uh what was once
this nice clean
8-bit mario same resolution uh nothing's
changed about the resolution but what
we've got is kind of this blurrier image
now a couple nuances about what's going
on here because
uh as with so many things in computer
science there's edge cases to handle
in this case it's a literal edge case
like what's going on at the edge
because if we just let this grid of
values fall off the side
and you know maybe we either don't count
them or we're multiplying them by zero
what ends up happening is we would only
be taking four ninths
of the given corner value and it's going
to end up disproportionately dark
which in some mathematical contexts
maybe that's what you want you would
want to treat the image as being
something where
outside of a certain domain it's
entirely zero
but when our eyes look at the blurred
image it doesn't quite seem right
because you see all of this black
or this sort of darker gray along the
side and what we
expect is that this was an image taken
in a broader context where what's
surrounding
you know mario's world is the same gray
that we would have thought
so in the problem set for today's uh not
today's lecture for this week's uh
uh lectures you've got well you've got
the task of basically
defining a function that will handle
this and a more general variety of
what's going on here
and one thing to think about is what
happens at that edge and
a typical convention in image processing
context would be that
when you're falling off the edge like
that you uh you just
uh multiply by the nearest value right
so if you see that it's
1 9 times 0 instead of falling off the
edge you take the
the nearest value in the image and that
would make the boundary of our
mario look a lot more gray so that's all
well and good
but there's another nuance that we might
want to handle here which is
you know if we're not in a super low
resolution context like this but if
we're in
something that's higher resolution and
we want to have a box that's a little
bit bigger
like maybe i have this 5x5 box that's
wandering along
it's a little bit strange to treat all
of the pixels in that 5x5 box with equal
weight
because the ones towards the center are
somehow more representative of what's
going on in that image
at that point than the ones that are
farther around
so for this example what i've actually
done if we zoom in here um
is i've given a grid of values that
aren't all the same you know it's not
all 1 divided by 25 in this case
but the middle one is 0.162 and out at
the
farther regions we've got 0.003
so when we multiply those by the
corresponding pixel values and then we
add them all together
we're basically taking a weighted sum
weighted according to how close to the
center it is
and that's a that's a way of saying that
okay it's okay for this pixel here to be
influenced by what's at the outer corner
but only by a little bit you know we
shouldn't we shouldn't get into it too
much
these specific values are coming from a
gaussian curve also known as a bell
curve
so you might imagine kind of this bell
curve surface sitting on top of the
image
and it's bulging right above the point
that we want and then it dissipates in
values
as you go away from that and that gets
us a much nicer notion of
uh averaging the pixels so that it's
like i said it's taking into account how
close they are to the point we want
the gaussian specifically has some
really nice mathematical properties that
we might talk about
a little later on in this lecture that
makes it really really quite nice for
doing this kind of operation
now this operation that we're doing as
you can infer from the title of the
video and
uh everything about this and what we
talked about last time
it's a convolution what you would say is
that the image on the right
the resulting values that we get are a
convolution of
the original image with the little grid
of values that we have here
okay so it's an operation that takes in
at least in an image processing context
two different grids of values maybe one
is rgb maybe one is numbers
they could both be numbers and it
combines them to get a new grid of
values
in other mathematical contexts we often
think of it as combining two functions
to get a new function
and when you're doing it with uh just
this little smaller window
it's quite common to refer to it as a
kernel so in this case we would say that
we convolved mario with a
gaussian kernel okay and at this point
you might sit back and think okay you
know that's all well and good i guess
with
different kinds of averages i could get
different sorts of blurring effects
going on in the images and
you know i guess there's some use cases
for blurring images like blurring out
faces
but it goes way beyond that actually
first of all smoothing out an image with
a gaussian kernel
is useful in a lot of contexts beyond
what you would expect
but the important thing i want you to
keep in mind here is not the specific
example
but um the general framework that's
being developed
where if we tweak what the values inside
that kernel are
we can start to do some more nuanced and
interesting things with images
and to get to that you know i say let's
just dive right into actually coding up
some examples here
so um i'm just going to be creating a
little pluto notebook like i did last
time here
and uh right now i've prepared it with
an image so i've created a large image
is loading a certain image of tom the
cat
and then i've shrunk it down mostly just
so that it's easier to see on the screen
but also that makes some of the things
faster to play with so if we just check
the size of the image
it's now a very small 500 by 399
and again by the way if any of you want
to ask questions
and you do so in the discord some of
them will be like forwarded in my
direction and i'll try to keep my eye on
if any of those have come in so feel
free to just do that whenever
and um oh i'm told my mic is peaking a
little bit
so let me let me just turn that down a
little bit give you a better
uh sound experience hopefully it's not
too unpleasant in any ways
it's always so finicky to get these live
streams to work properly
but we want to actually do this uh
convolving operation right we want to
actually see what happens when we mess
around with different kernels
so first of all to get a given kernel
there's this library that i'm going to
use
we've got all of our definitions down
here for various functions i'm going to
have
but i'm going to be using one called
image filtering and in
it it has this module called kernel
and we can pull up the documentation for
it you know just using the live docs
here
where it tells us the various different
functions it has in there and among them
is this gaussian which is exactly what
you want but it already tells you that
there's more interesting kernels that
can be played with
and if i create a gaussian and i specify
two different standard deviations one in
the x direction one in the y direction
what it gives me is a grid of values so
we take a look and this type is a five
by five
offset array okay so essentially it's an
array of floats
but the offset just means that um the
way that you index into it
let's give it a name like kernel
is such that the middle value is at zero
zero so if i called kernel of zero
zero i get that middle value that we
actually saw in the animation point one
six two
um and then if we take you know
something like negative two which
usually
you know you can't index at zero much
less below zero
uh with julia arrays in this context
it's specifically offset
that doesn't matter too much just wanted
to say in case you were wondering what
that term means
what we actually want is a nice way to
take a look at what this kernel is
so i wrote a very simple function just
called show colored kernel
that's basically pulling out the
positive part and making it green
and then if a kernel has negative part
it's going to pull it out as red
so you can take a look at the details if
you want for that later
but all i want is for you to think about
okay
we've got this little grid of values
that's very peaked at one point and then
kind of dissipates out
we're gonna have it march along the
image of the cat here
and what's that gonna do and you already
know what it's going to do because we've
played around with mario
but the idea is that as we tweak what
this kernel is we'll get some more
interesting things
so what you will write in the problem
set this week is a function called
convolve
it will do exactly this it'll take in an
image it'll take in this kernel of
values
and it'll produce a new image which in
this context
is a little bit blurrier now because
this is a small kernel
you know maybe it's not as visible but
if i changed it to be a gaussian
with standard deviation 3 the library is
smart and it knows to make it
a little bit bigger if i want it to so
now it's a 13 by 13
array and we see that it indeed does
make it notably blurrier
and we could go to an extreme we could
say you know i want the standard
deviation to be
quite a bit larger so maybe 10 by 10
and this gets me a much larger array so
that little gaussian
curve that we're imagining marching
along the image that would now be 41 by
and the result that you get is that
every pixel is really influenced by a
lot around it
very much like you took a lens and you
um you unfocused the image
now while we're here and because this is
a class about computational thinking
let's think a little bit about
computational complexity because
in order to process that image there
julia's generally pretty fast
um but this took 9.5 seconds now a big
part of that is maybe because i wrote
this convolved function
less efficiently than it could be we'll
talk later this lecture about
like very clever things that are done to
make it more efficient
but just in principle if you want to
like actively think about how many
operations are taking place here
uh it's a fun little exercise to think
about because the size of our image
right it looks like it's not too big
it's 500 by 399. which means if we take
the product of those two values let's
give that's
the number of pixels um so if we
multiply that by
the number of values in the kernel so
the product
for the size array on the kernel
it's actually quite a few different
multiplications that have to happen
through this whole process because
remember
every time that little window is sitting
on top of a pixel you're multiplying all
of those neighboring values and then
you're adding them up
so in this context it looks like we've
got you know thousand million
just for one simple small image like 300
million multiplications have to happen
so that's just a thing to think about
here is that as the kernel gets larger
it unless you do something clever it
will by default take a lot longer to
process images especially if they're
higher resolution
but before we talk about how to
diminish that kind of complexity let's
just play around with what happens if i
change this kernel
so actually before i even show you i
think i want to do this as a live quiz
so that might be a little bit fun where
um we were doing a couple of these in
the intro animation just
some warm-up questions but as the first
real question
uh i'm going to give you a sample kernel
okay i'm not going to show you what it
does or tell you what it does
but i want you to actually try to think
about what this would do
okay so it's going to be a little 3x3
grid and
it's got a lot of negative values around
the boundary and the center value is a
7.
okay so it's going to be seven at the
center and then some negative values
around it
specifically one for the immediately
adjacent neighbors and then
negative point five for all of those
around it
and uh at this point if you go to
itempool.com3b1b
live you can place a vote we're seeing
the statistics on how other people are
answering
and i'm i'm actually genuinely curious
what people will
uh will say to this one so this is going
to be our first example of a
non-blurring
well maybe i shouldn't say that maybe
it's obvious from the context the
blurring isn't going to be the right
answer
but while you while you answer that i'm
going to go ahead and type that up
into our notebook just to have prepared
and also while you answer it think about
what
aspects of this kernel you could try to
compute
to get a loose sense of how it would
behave in different uh regions of the
image
you know if it's in a monochromatic
region what does it look like if it's in
a region where there's a lot going on
what does it look like like try to try
to think through some examples in your
head
and that's probably around the amount of
time i want to spend
although let's let's just take a look if
there's any questions in the doc
to uh to answer while we're waiting
there
is it possible to reconstruct the
original image from the blurred one
i i don't think so um
that's an interesting question we'll
have to ask the other professor i
definitely don't think so because you
can take this to an extreme
where uh it feels like you're definitely
losing out on information
there's other things that you can do to
it though like the fast fourier
transform would be an example where you
can recover the image exactly
but those feel like you know very rare i
don't want to say that offhandedly
because
i don't know quite off the top of my
head one of the other props who's
smarter than i
might come in to answer um and the
second one
uh how does convolving an image with a
kernel directly relate to convolving two
functions
glad that you asked that um i'll talk
about that in just a little bit actually
what the
relationship between image processing
definition of convolution is and then
how you see it in some other
mathematical contexts
it's essentially the same idea though
that you have one thing that's marching
across another
you multiply corresponding values and
then you add them up
it's it's really the same operation
modulo like one or two small conventions
all right so if we go back to our quiz
i'll go ahead and
see what the answers turn out to be here
and
fascinating so it looks like most people
thought that it would detect edges
but if we actually play with this if we
go to our notebook here
and i've gone ahead and written in the
kernel so
that same grid of values that i gave you
where seven in the center and then some
negatives around
the effect that it has on the picture of
the cat here is it actually
kind of sharpens it up so if we look
previously his chest is very fluffy very
soft
but over here what it's done is really
accentuated the differences between one
piece of fur in the next
now for those of you who did answer edge
detecting you're definitely on the right
track
uh but one small thing that you could do
to kind of check what the behavior of
this kernel might be
is to notice uh what the sum of all of
those values are
the spelling kernel here so if we add
them all up they equal one
which is much the same that you would do
with any kind of um
weighted average if you have all the
weights they've got to be one
and what that means is that if you're in
a region of the image without any edges
okay you're in like a totally
monochromatic spot if you add up all of
the values and you're multiplying them
and the sum for the kernel is one well
that means that you're just going to get
the original color back
the circumstances under which this does
something non-obvious
are when there's a lot of variation near
a point so if you have one point that's
um let's say a very bright pixel
and then it's surrounded by very dark
pixels that will end up looking quite
bright because the dark ones aren't
subtracting off in the way that other
things are
now if you want to think about edge
detection stuff there's a couple
standard kernels that we might play with
for that so one of the simplest
would be what's called a sobel kernel
and in this context it's yelling at us
because what it returns isn't actually a
single kernel but a pair of them
so i might pull out just one or maybe
the second index
um and let's let's go ahead and
visualize this kernel see
first of all we've got that the sum is
zero so that's telling us something
interesting
let me do my show colored kernel
great so we see it's got positive values
on the right
and it's got negative values on the left
but crucially
now if we add up all of those values it
comes up to zero so if you would imagine
taking this kernel and you put it over a
monochromatic part of the image
it's going to come out completely black
which sort of matches with what we see
here where
at first it looks like it's completely
turning the image black but
let's think a little bit more about what
we would expect this specific kernel to
do
so if we've got our image in mind of
taking you know a specific
little grid of values and what are we
doing we're just kind of marching it
across the image
what would you expect to be required for
this to end up as a positive number well
if we're adding up some positive values
on the right
and then we're subtracting off whatever
they multiply on the left
then if you have some region where it
goes from being very dark
to being very bright that's going to be
where you get positive values
but notice you can also get negative
values here if you had a lot of
brightness on the left
and then a lot of darkness on the right
what this convolution would give you
is a negative value so that's important
to keep in mind
just because we're displaying these
convolutions as rgb images
doesn't mean that's always the right way
to see it because in this context when
we've convolved
our fluffy cat with something that
occasionally puts out negative values
the way that the rgb type is going to
treat that is
not necessarily going to be displayed in
a way that shows everything that's going
on
so what i could do instead is take an
absolute value of everything happening
not an absolute value of the convolution
so we've got our convolution take an
absolute value
of what's sitting there and that's
basically if i take the absolute value
of an rgb
it's um treating it like a vector
getting the norm this gives us a grid of
values
i still want to see it as if it was
colors so i'm going to tell pluto hey
i want you to think of these as
grayscale values
and i might even scale them up a little
bit just because i'm especially not sure
how the youtube compression is handling
this all
but this will really just accentuate out
all of the points where
this sobolfilter convolved across the
image ends up non-zero
and what you see is all of the points
where there's a lot of micro variations
as you move uh from left to right kind
of like the uh
you know the different color fur that
happens on the chest
that's where you start to get a lot of
activity
and if we take the other thing that this
kernel.sobel returned
it basically gives us the horizontal
version of that okay so as you move
up and down for example right around the
whiskers that's going to be where you
get a lot of this variation
and that's what's going to make the
convolution of the image with this
specific
kernel something non-zero so the point
here is that you know you can do
blurring you can do sharpening you can
do
edge detecting type things and you can
really get more and more sophisticated
as you tweak
the specific values of this kernel it's
a really powerful tool
beyond just a moving average many of you
may have heard of the idea of a
convolutional neural network
this is in a context where what you want
is for a machine to learn
specific kernels so rather than hand
baking one like
handing it a gaussian or handing it a
sobel instead you try to have it learn
which kernels are going to pull out some
meaningful information from an image
so it's a very good building block to
add up on top of all of that
now one thing to point out while we're
looking at this
sobo filter is unlike the other ones
it's asymmetric
so that it looks different on the left
than it does on the right whereas
a simple gaussian blur or a box blur it
doesn't matter how you rotate it
and you might think this doesn't matter
but it does end up highlighting
a different convention that you'll
sometimes find so
in mathematical contexts instead of
doing the thing that you would expect
which is having this kernel actively
march across the image
we often think of whatever the uh
convolved term is
as being rotated around so i'll show you
what i mean if we have over here
we've got our kernel it's marching along
the image what you actually want to
imagine the the picture to actually hold
in your head
for convolutions in a mathematical
setting is to basically flip it entirely
around
so if the original kernel had the green
on the right and the red on the left
really you're kind of flipping it around
before you have it march across the
image
and then do the same thing where you
multiply corresponding terms and you add
them all up
and at first that might seem like a very
strange thing to do
why would the convention in any context
work out like that
and indeed in some image processing ones
they just define convolutions to do the
thing that you would expect
um but i do want to take a little moment
to explain why you sometimes see it this
way
and why it actually gives you these
really nice mathematical properties
i don't know if i'll have uh full time
to delve into the details here
but we're going to start by talking
about something that seems
totally unrelated to image processing
which is to multiply two different
polynomials together so for this one let
me actually pop back to our live quiz
and just have you do a little bit of
active thinking
so the question asks that you
consider the following expression you've
got a certain polynomial term
whose coefficients are k0 k1 k2 and then
we're multiplying it by an infinite
series okay just an infinite power
series
with different um powers of x in there
and it wants you to just look at one
specific term what is the constant for
the x cubed
term okay so think about that you know
choose your answer as you're thinking
about that
maybe i'll start talking through how
you'd multiply this out
and again this might seem extremely
unrelated to image processing
and it's actually um it's actually
closer than you might think
for reasons that i hope to be able to
get into but a half hour is an awfully
short time for a lecture i do have to
say
so k zero times a one
is just going to give you the constant
term any other pair of terms that you
have in here
isn't going to uh is going to involve
some kind of x
so if we try to organize things in terms
of what their constants are
you know we've got uh just
simple term for the constant and then if
you start thinking about what's the term
in front of
x well we can take k0 times a1 and then
k1 times a0
those are the two things in the product
they're going to result in x just to the
power of one
and you know i think a lot of you kind
of know how to do this we're just doing
a foil basically between two different
polynomials one of them just
happens to be infinite and you know the
next term is going to be the
answer to the live quiz so let me go
ahead and pop over there
see what most people are saying here so
it looks like we've got
92 93 people answering correctly
um that it's a which basically is just
marching through all of the pairs so
that the index on the k
added together with the index on the a
is equal to three
and uh those of you who answered b it's
like completely in the right thought
it's just that we're multiplying by a
quadratic um polynomial instead of
multiplying by
something that goes on forever as well
so there is no k3 term
that's the that's the only distractor in
that one question
and so you know you know how this goes
we've got
various different terms that we could
get it's a nice big product
a way that you could think about
multiplying two polynomials like this
that's actually heavy heavily related
now to
all the ideas that we were just talking
about is i'm going to take a copy of
that polynomial
and then i'm going to take this
quadratic but i want a copy of the
quadratic which is
turned around so i'm putting the k2 term
on the left and then the k0 term on the
right
we could imagine doing exactly what the
little kernel for our image was doing
just having it march across
where first here we we align the k zero
with the a0 terms
we multiply them and then we have it
march one further
and we align the k1 with the a0 and the
k0 with the a1
multiply the corresponding terms and add
them together and that's
exactly what we get for our next term
here then we have it march along once
more
play the same game multiply
corresponding terms add them all
together
and what you see is that the terms in
the new polynomial
could be described as a convolution
between the terms
in the original polynomials that we had
but notice that in order for that to
work we needed this convention where
one of the polynomials was flipped
around before you do this marching
process
so because that's how it comes up in a
lot of mathematical contexts this ends
up being a convention
more broadly but it does actually have a
little bit of um
influence on on the image processing
context because there's a heavy analogy
here between
the values k in some little polynomial
and the values of our kernel
and then thinking of all of these values
a as being kind of like
pixel values right except instead of
storing them in different spots
it's kind of like we're storing them
next to an associated power of x
now that might seem like a strange thing
to do with pixels and indeed we never
really do that with pixels
but one thing that we actually do do is
take a um
a slight variation of this where instead
of multiplying each pixel value
by x we might multiply it by this e to
the two pi
i times some sort of frequency term and
as we take the power of that
you get this thing that rotates across
and it lets you pull out frequency
information from the uh
image now i'm not expecting uh people
watching this to necessarily know
about fourier transforms or fourier
series if you want to know
you know i hear there's a youtube
channel that covers some of these topics
that
you could watch some of the videos of
but at a very high level i do want to
try to finish the lecture showing you
something
really cool about convolutions and about
making them more
computationally efficient than you might
think is possible and the only things
you need to know about
fourier transforms is we're doing
something very analogous to power series
and then mathematically it behaves very
similarly
so all we're doing is taking these
values and multiplying them by something
it's not x but it's something that we
have successive powers of
and what that means is that if we do
that to two different
arrays to two different collections of
values
multiplying the two results corresponds
to convolving the original terms
so for example right when we take the
polynomial that was generated by k
and we multiply it by the polynomial
that was generated by these a terms
we get a new polynomial where each term
is a convolution between a and k
same thing would happen if we replaced x
with something um
like this e to the two pi i stuff all of
the terms from one
if you take this collection of the terms
from one what's going to be called the
fourier transform of that thing
and you multiply it by the fourier
transform of the other
it corresponds to convolving the
original terms now this will be a little
bit easier to see if we
just again actually pull up a notebook
and play around with it
so what i'm going to do is let's just
remind ourselves what the image looked
like
this was the cat and i've just written a
very simple
plot 1d fourier spectrum
oh asking me to update my software in
the middle of a lecture
how rude all right so
uh again i'm not necessarily expecting
everyone to know
what a fourier transform is but at a
high level i want to be able to describe
what information about the image it's
pulling out so
tom the cat is a rather soft image with
not a lot of variation happening from
left to right
so if i go through and i try to ask um
you know is there very very fine detail
a lot of
high frequency changes happening as we
move from left to right
there's not necessarily going to be a
lot of information there
now i don't know why
this is taking as long as it is to
process
all right maybe it had to pre-compile
the function for the first time
but tom doesn't actually produce a very
interesting fourier transform and he
doesn't give a good in
uh instinct for what information is
being pulled out so what we could do
instead
i'll go ahead and get rid of his uh
convolution term there
is take a more interesting image so i've
prepared one
that's just a herd of zebra
so this heard of zebra we've got lots of
stripes as you move from the left to the
right
kernel by the way i'm just going to
prepare ourselves a gaussian kernel here
let's get a gaussian that's maybe you
know this nine by nine thing
if we look at the uh this fourier
information associated with the image
the only thing i want you to notice is
that as you go away from zero
you actually have higher values so for
example it kind of peaks up
a little above 50 here which almost
certainly corresponds with the frequency
of the stripes themselves
as we move from left to right now the
reason i bring all of this up
is to try to highlight what happens when
we take the convolution of this image
okay so i'm going to create a new image
called conv-m
that's going to convolve the image with
that kernel
which we define to be a gaussian and
as you expect it's a blurrier version of
the of the zebras
but now if we do the same thing we plot
this 1d fourier spectrum
but we do it on the convolved version of
the image what we get looks very similar
to the original
but notice how what's happening around
the edges have been pushed down
and that's a way of saying all the high
frequency stuff happening with the image
all that finer detail
is no longer there so now it's behaving
a lot more like the image of the cat
that was soft all around
and there's actually something much more
specific that's happening here where
it turns out that the uh the fourier
transform of this
gaussian kernel is another gaussian
curve
specifically in such a way that if you
have a really narrow gaussian the
fourier transform
is something really broad if you have a
broad one it gives you something really
narrow
and if we just look at the gauss the the
fourier information just the frequency
information
and we multiply it by a bell curve kind
of squishing down what's at the outer
regions
that gets us the same fourier
information
and remember how a little bit earlier i
was talking about the computational
complexity here how as we have a really
big kernel
it requires a lot of multiplications it
turns out if instead we
first translate things to describing it
in terms of the frequencies of the image
where convolution is just like
multiplication so we can just
multiply the two functions as functions
just pixel by pixel
and then we take it back it gives us a
much faster way to do this operation
and given that this is a course about
computational thinking i think you know
there is a certain general principle to
be had in that
where finding different ways to
represent your information actually can
sometimes help you do things much faster
now here i'm plotting just um a very
one-dimensional thing it's kind of
marching across the image from left to
right
but we could uh show what did i write
like heat map 2d fourier spectrum and
again i'll share this notebook if you
want to play with it
um we can do kind of a two-dimensional
analog
where the information that comes out of
this again i think it has to pre-compile
it
is essentially saying what's the level
of detail happening
both in the vertical and horizontal
direction so in this context
you know we get this strange galactic
image
and if we apply it to the smoothed out
version
the convolved image uh not con
image conv image what we see is that it
actually pushes down the values
that are far away and concentrates us
towards the center and just to kind of
see the contrast if we had started off
with a much softer image
started off with something like tom
he's soft to begin with this uh
this fourier spectrum which again it's
okay if it's not crystal clear what it's
supposed to represent
all i want you to know is that the
farther away you are from the center
the brightness of those values
corresponds to the level of detail
happening
that this is what like a softer image
looks like and as you multiply by
a gaussian in this fourier space it
pushes you towards this smoother looking
spectrum
and that's a much faster operation so
often in the standard libraries for
convolutions they don't do the naive
thing when you have a large kernel
instead they do this more sophisticated
thing
and again you can see kind of what
effect this has had so here the version
of the function convolved that i wrote
by the way
it's not doing the sophisticated thing
it's just doing the naive you have the
little grid of values march across and
you have them uh multiply and add as you
need
and you'll be doing that in the problem
set uh this week
so uh i think oh man a half hour is such
a short time
all right i've already run out uh but
that is the basics of
image convolutions and the main thing i
want you to take away here
is a a simple tool that seemed like it
was specific at first where we were just
doing moving averages
if you abstract in the right way right
you write it so that rather than just
hard coding all of the moving average
functionality you take it out where
this general convolution principle can
be applied as its own and we tweak
some data we tweak the kernel that lets
you do qualitatively different things
with your data
so in this case it let us do things like
blurring like sharpening like edge
detecting
and then the other thing is that when
you represent your data in distinct ways
so uh in this context if we were taking
the fourier
information taking this frequency
information sometimes that actually lets
you do things
much faster even though you're doing
under the hood
um well not under the hood like in the
abstract sense you're doing the same
operations on the data
one domain can often be different from
another and how it behaves
so with that i'm going to call it an
into this first lecture
um for the mit students in the course
we're going to do uh like a zoom call
that's basically the profs um
just discussing more of this material in
person so you can interact there
as always there's the discord so please
do jump into the discord ask questions
have discussion
and i will see you next week and enjoy
the first problem set
[Music]
do
you